A Guide to the Douglas P. Murray papers FA1122
Rockefeller Archive Center
Douglas P. Murray papers
1962, 1967, 1969-2011
Rockefeller Archive Center
Murray, Douglas P.
National Committee on United States-China Relations
FA1122
15.72 Cubic Feet 35 document boxes
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
Douglas P. Murray attended Yale University where he received his BA in Behavioral Science in 1958 and his MA in Southeast Asian Studies in 1961. He went on to receive his PhD in International Development Education from Stanford University, with his dissertation on Chinese education in Singapore.
Throughout his career he has held several positions related to Asia and China: Director of the US-China Relations Program at Stanford University, 1975-1981, Vice President of the East-West Center in Honolulu, 1981-1984, Executive Secretary of the Committee on International Relations Studies with the People's Republic of China, and President of China Institute in America, 1986-1988.
He first traveled to Asia in 1958 to teach English at New Asia College, Hong Kong, through the Yale-China Association, and has taught at New Zealand's Victoria University and in Singapore while serving as Representative of The Asia Foundation.
He joined the National Committee on United States-China Relations first as Program Director and Vice President, 1975-1981, and has served as a member of its Board and Executive Committee. He was President of NCUSCR in 1997.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 3 series: Series 1-National Committee on United States-China Relations (NCUSCR), Administrative Series 2-National Committee on United States-China Relations (NCUSCR), Environmental Programs Series 3-Committee on International Relations Studies with the People's Republic of China (CIRSPRC)
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: correspondence, travel logs, brochures and pamphlets, photographs, and newspaper articles.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection was donated to Rockefeller Archive Center by Douglas P. Murrary in 2015.
- National Committee on United States-China Relations (NCUSCR), Administrative, 1962, 1967, 1969-2011; 1
  - Board of Directors, Meeting, 1970 September 17-1979 September 17 (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting, 1980 October 22-1988 December 6 (Box 2, Folder 17-26)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting, 1989 August 1-1995 November 27-28 (Box 3, Folder 27-34)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting, 1996 November 21-22-2003 November 13 (Box 4, Folder 35-42)
  - Board of Directors, Meeting, 2004 November 11-2007 May 15 (Box 5, Folder 43-46)
  - Annual Members Meeting, 1972 May 16-2002 December 5 (Box 5, Folder 47-62)
  - Annual Members Meeting, 2004 November 12-2006 November 9 (Box 6, Folder 63-65)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting, 1970 November 5-1977 April 18 (Box 6, Folder 66-80)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting, 1978 May 8-1988 May 26 (Box 7, Folder 81-92)
  - Executive Committee, Meeting, 1990 December 3-2005 May 26 (Box 8, Folder 93-103)
  - General Correspondence, 1973-1980 (Box 9, Folder 104-110)
  - General Correspondence, 1981-1983, 1993, 1996-1999 (Box 10, Folder 111-116)
  - Program Summary, 1968-1969 (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - Phamplets, 1972, 1974-1977 (Box 10, Folder 1118)
  - United States Liaison Office, Peking, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Budgets, 1967, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Roundtable Meeting, "Prospect and Problems of Developing Relations with China", 1971 January 22-23 (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Administrative Files, 1971-1972, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 122)
  - Annual Reports, 1969-1974 (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Members & Staff, 1972, 1974-1975, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Members, 1997 February 12 (Box 11, Folder 125)
  - Exchanges, Miscellaneous, 1972-1973, 1975, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - American Zoetrope & Media Consultants, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Trade Background, 1962, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 128)
  - Trade Initiative, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 129)
  - Future Structure and Directions of the National Committee, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 130)
  - General Documents, Reports, & History, 1969-1971, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 131)
  - Outreach, The Johnson Foundation, Wingspread, 1975, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 132)
  - National Conference of Mayors, 1975 September (Box 11, Folder 133)
  - Archaeological Finds of People's Republic of China, 1975 (Box 11, Folder 134)
  - Basketball Teams, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Basketball, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 136)
  - People's Republic of China Soccer Team, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 137)
  - Tennis Team, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 138)
  - U. S. Track & Field Team to People's Republic of China, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 139)
  - World Affairs Education Delegation, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 140)
  - Performing Arts Troupe, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 141)
  - Performing Arts Troupe, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 142)
  - Members Tour Groups, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 143)
  - People's Republic of China Radio and Television Delegation, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 144)
  - Women Leaders, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 145)
  - Provincial Education Delegation, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 146)
  - Municipal Administrators, 1978 (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - The Johnson Foundation, Wingspread, 1977, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - Delegations, Miscellaneous, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - Asian Art Museum of San Francisco, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 150)
  - The Joint Committee of the U. S. Table Tennis Association and the National Committee on U. S.-China Relations Meeting, 1971 September 1 (Box 12, Folder 151)
  - Foundation Package, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 152)
  - United States-China Dialogue, 1984 September 6-9 (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - Murray, Douglas P., Resumes and Miscellaneous, 1970, 1972-1974, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 154)
  - People's Republic of China, International Relations Organizations, 1982-1985 (Box 13, Folder 155)
  - Beijing Office Proposal, 1988, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 156)
  - U. S. Congress, Trouble, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 157)
  - Reports, 1974, 1979-1981 (Box 13, Folder 158)
  - Fiscal Reports and Board Materials, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 159)
  - Reports and Board Materials, 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 160-161)
  - Reports and Board Materials, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 162)
  - Education Subcommittee, Memorandum, 1986-1987 (Box 14, Folder 163)
  - Education, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 164)
  - Nominating Committeee, 1992-1997 (Box 14, Folder 165-166)
  - Search Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 14, Folder 167)
  - Chairman Search, 2000-2001 (Box 14, Folder 168)
  - Fourth United States China Dialogue, Discussion on Sino-U. S. Relations, 1990 February 26-March 1 (Box 14, Folder 169)
  - A Mission for the National Committee on U. S.-China Relations, 1984 October (Box 14, Folder 170)
  - Provincial Colleges and Universities Delegation from the People's Republic of China, 1985 October 19-November 10 (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - Board Materials, 2002-2004 (Box 14, Folder 172)
  - Trip, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 173)
  - Notes on China Trip, 1972-1973 (Box 15, Folder 174)
  - Board Trip to China, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 175-176)
  - Executive Committee, Program Planning, 1984-1986 (Box 15, Folder 177)
  - General Mailings (Luncheon Series, Announcements, etc.), 1984-1985 (Box 15, Folder 178)
  - Board Related Materials, 1986-1990, 1994-1997 (Box 15, Folder 179-181)
  - Exchanges, 1972-1997, 1998 April 15 (Box 15, Folder 182)
  - Audit Committee, 1995, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 183)
  - Nominating Committee, 1989, 1997-2008 (Box 16, Folder 184-187)
  - Audit and Compensation Committees, 1992-1998 (Box 16, Folder 188)
  - Staffing, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 189)
  - Committees' Materials, 1989, 1991-1992, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 190-191)
  - Programs and Board Related Materials, 1992-1994 (Box 17, Folder 192-194)
  - Berris, Jan, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - Administrative, Miscellaneous, 1998-2000, 2004-2005 (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - American-China Society (ACS), 1999 (Box 17, Folder 197)
  - Strategy Committee and Fallout, 2000, 2002 (Box 17, Folder 198)
  - Directors/Members Memoranda, 1999-2003 (Box 17, Folder 199)
  - By-Laws, 1990 March 13 (Box 17, Folder 200-201)
  - Gala, 2006 (Box 18, Folder 202)
  - Board of Directors and Members Meetings and Related Materials, 2004, 2006-2011 (Box 18, Folder 203-204)
  - Briefing Materials for the Trustees of Lingnan University Delegation to Hong Kong and China, 1986 May 31-June 4 (Box 18, Folder 205)
  - Kennedy, Anthony and Legal Studies Program in China, 2002 (Box 18, Folder 206)
  - The Exchange, Newsletter, Vol. 7, No. 3, 2003 May-August (Box 18, Folder 207)
  - Young Leaders Forum (YLF), 2001-2002 (Box 18, Folder 208)
  - Programs, Miscellaneous, 1998-2002 (Box 18, Folder 209)
  - Reports and Related Materials, 2002-2003 (Box 18, Folder 210)
  - Delegation of the China Institute of Contemporary International Relations (CICIR), 2005 (Box 18, Folder 211)
  - Delegation of the Shanghai Institute for International Studies, 2005-2006 (Box 18, Folder 212)
  - Shieh, Shawn, 2011 July 19 (Box 18, Folder 213)
  - Manchuria Trip, 2005 (Box 18, Folder 214)
- National Committee on United States-China Relations (NCUSCR), Environmental Programs, 1987-2001, 2004-2005; 2
  - Rongji, Zhu, The Forum for Environment and Development, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 215)
  - Environmental, Woodrow Wilson Center Foundations, 1998-1999 (Box 19, Folder 216)
  - Dayong, Qian, 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 217)
  - Hu, Kang-Ping, 1992, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 218)
  - Hu, Kang-Ping, 1992, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 218A)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from access - Confidential material
  - Smil, Vaclav, 1991-1994 (Box 19, Folder 219)
  - Suttmeier, Pete, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 220)
  - Segal, Gerald, Douglas Murray's Article, 1993-1994 (Box 19, Folder 221)
  - Civil Society/Environmental Programs, 1998-2001, 2004-2005 (Box 19, Folder 222)
  - Gore, Albert and Foundations, 1997-1999 (Box 19, Folder 223)
  - Report on Lake Baikal Region Sustainable Development, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 224)
  - Ussuri River Project, 1993-1994 October (Box 19, Folder 225-226)
  - Ussuri River Project, 1994 November-1998 (Box 20, Folder 227-229)
  - Ussuri, MacArthur Foundation, 1993 (Box 20, Folder 230)
  - Ussuri, Trip, 1991-994 (Box 20, Folder 231)
  - Ussuri, Hong Kong Trip, 1992-1993 (Box 20, Folder 232)
  - Ussuri, Proposals, Grants, and Budgets, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 233)
  - Chinese Correspondence, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 234)
  - Russian Correspondence, 1994 (Box 20, Folder 235)
  - U. S. Team Correspondence and Reports, 1994-1995 (Box 21, Folder 236)
  - Ussuri, Bruce Marcot Reports, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 237)
  - Ussuri, 1993 Trip Planning and Management, 1992-1994 (Box 21, Folder 238)
  - Sino-Russian Visit, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 239)
  - Field Work, 1994 (Box 21, Folder 240)
  - Ussuri, Foundation Proposals and Reports, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 241-242)
  - Ussuri, General Correspondence, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 243)
  - Ussuri, Wingspread Conference, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 244)
  - Ussuri, Trip Planning & Management, 1992-1994 (Box 22, Folder 245-246)
  - International Conference on the Ussuri River Watershed Sustainable Development Strategy Initiation, 1998 May 25 (Box 22, Folder 247)
  - Agreement, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 248)
  - Agreements, Ussuri, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 249)
  - Ussuri, Contacts, Mailing Lists China, 1988, 1990, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 250)
  - Ussuri, Contacts, Mailing Lists Russia, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 251)
  - Tumen River, 1991-1993, 1995 (Box 22, Folder 252)
  - Tumen River, Articles, 1994-1995 (Box 22, Folder 253)
  - International Crane Foundation (ICF), Jim Harris, 1992-1993 (Box 22, Folder 254)
  - Tumen River Project, 1998 (Box 22, Folder 255)
  - Northern Forum, 1990, 1992-1994 (Box 22, Folder 256)
  - U. S. Interests in China's Environment, 1992-1993 (Box 23, Folder 257)
  - China, Costal, 1989-1990, 1992 (Box 23, Folder 258)
  - Environmental Seminar, China Mayoral Delegation Visit, 1990 July 15-18 (Box 23, Folder 259)
  - Preparation, Proposals, Drafts, 1987, 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 260)
  - Ussuri, Correspondence and Articles, 1996-1998 (Box 23, Folder 261)
  - Reports, Land Use and China, 1992, 1994-1995 (Box 23, Folder 262)
  - Northeast Asia, Planning Meeting, 1992 June 25, 1990-1992 (Box 23, Folder 263)
  - China-Russia, Environment & General, Articles, 1989-1990, 1992-1997 (Box 24, Folder 264-265)
  - Mailings Sent, 1994 (Box 24, Folder 266)
  - Ussuri, China-Russia, Reference, 1992-1993 (Box 24, Folder 267)
  - Ussuri Watershed Project, Background Materials, 1992 (Box 24, Folder 268)
  - Ussuri, Budgets, 1993 (Box 24, Folder 269)
  - Ussuri, Related Background Materials, 1993-1994 (Box 24, Folder 270)
  - Ussuri, Reference, 1993, 1999-2001 (Box 24, Folder 271)
  - Ecologically Sustainable Development, Inc. (ESD), 1994, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 272)
  - Flood Project, 1998-1999 (Box 24, Folder 273)
  - Flood, Heilongjiang Province, 1999 (Box 24, Folder 274)
  - Reports, China and Water/Flood, 1992, 1996-2000 (Box 24, Folder 275)
  - Environmental, Miscellaneous Projects, 1989-1991, 1993, 1996 (Box 25, Folder 276)
  - World Resources Institute (WRI), 1994 (Box 25, Folder 277)
  - World Resources Institute, China Trip 1992, 1992-1993 (Box 25, Folder 278)
  - U. S. Interests, 1992-1993 (Box 25, Folder 279)
  - Ussuri, Project, 1997-1998 (Box 25, Folder 280)
  - Proceedings of Eco-environment Investigation, 1998 (Box 25, Folder 281)
  - International Conference on Environmental Development, Beijing, 1990 (Box 25, Folder 282)
  - Lees, Martin, Conferences, 1989-1992, 1994, 1996 (Box 26, Folder 283-284)
  - Ussuri, Chinese Papers, 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 285)
  - Ussuri, Russian and American Papers, 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 286)
  - Institute of International Education, 1990-1991 (Box 26, Folder 287)
  - China Energy, Battelle Pacific Northwest Laboratories, 1992 (Box 26, Folder 288)
  - Expenses, 1990-1991 (Box 26, Folder 289)
  - China Workshop, Environment, 1990-1991 (Box 27, Folder 290)
  - Williams, Robert H., 1990-1991 (Box 27, Folder 291)
  - Williams, Robert H. The Potential for Reducing CO2 Emissions with New Energy Technology, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 292)
  - Williams, Robert H., Reports, 1990-1992 (Box 27, Folder 293-294)
  - Kunin, Madeleine M., Trip to China, 1991 (Box 27, Folder 295)
  - Kunin, Madeleine M., 1990-1992 (Box 28, Folder 296)
  - State Planning Commission (SPC), 1990-1991 (Box 28, Folder 297)
  - Economy, Elizabeth, 1991-1992 (Box 28, Folder 298)
  - Costle, Douglas M., 1991 (Box 28, Folder 299)
  - Workshop, Local Economy & Global Ecology, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 300)
  - Trip Papers from China, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 301)
  - Chandler, William U., 1990-1991 (Box 28, Folder 302)
  - Global Climate Change, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 303)
  - Tripp, James T. B., Environmental Defense Fund, Inc., 1988, 1990-1991, 1993 (Box 28, Folder 304)
  - Jie, Gao, 1991 (Box 28, Folder 305)
  - Trip, 1991 (Box 29, Folder 306)
  - Participants & Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 29, Folder 307)
  - Report, Introduction to Environmental Risk Assessment, 1990-1991 (Box 29, Folder 308)
  - Budget, Administrative Materials, 1991-1992 (Box 29, Folder 309)
  - Conference Reports, 1991-1993 (Box 29, Folder 310-311)
  - Business Cards, Miscellaneous (Box 29, Folder 312)
  - Conferences and Luncheons, Related Materials, 1990, 1992-1993 (Box 29, Folder 313)
- Committee on International Relations Studies with the People's Republic of China (CIRSPRC), 1976, 1978, 1981-1989, 1992; 3
  - General Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 30, Folder 314-318)
  - Graduate Studies Application, 1987-1988 (Box 30, Folder 319)
  - Graduate Studies Application, 1987-1988 (Box 30, Folder 319A)
  - General Correspondence & Reports, 1986-1988 (Box 31, Folder 320-321)
  - General Correspondence & Reports, 1986-1988 (Box 31, Folder 321A)
  - Proposal, 1984 (Box 31, Folder 322)
  - Reference, 1987 (Box 31, Folder 323)
  - Beida, 1985-1986 (Box 31, Folder 324)
  - Beijing Institute for International Strategic Studies (BIISS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 325)
  - Foreign Affairs College (FAC), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 326)
  - Institute of Contemporary International Relations, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 327)
  - Institute for International Studies (IIS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 328)
  - Centre for International Studies, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 329)
  - Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 330)
  - Fudan University, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 331)
  - Shanghai Institute for International Studies (SIIS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 332)
  - Shanghai Academy of Social Sciences (SASS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 333)
  - Shanghai Academy of Social Sciences (SASS), 1986 (Box 31, Folder 333A)
  - Nankai University, 1982, 1986 (Box 31, Folder 334)
  - Beijing, 1985 (Box 31, Folder 335)
  - International Relations Meeting, 1982-1984 (Box 32, Folder 336)
  - Trip, General, People's Republic of China, 1986 (Box 32, Folder 337)
  - Shanghai, 1981, 1985 (Box 32, Folder 338)
  - China Trip, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 339-340)
  - China Trip, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 339A)
  - Meeting, New York City, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 341-342)
  - China Updates, National Association for Foreign Student Affairs (NAFSA), 1985 (Box 32, Folder 343)
  - Report, Supporting International Studies in China, Harry Harding, 1992 (Box 32, Folder 344)
  - Other Chinese Organizations, 1981, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 345)
  - Steering Committee and Related Materials, 1983-1984 (Box 32, Folder 346)
  - Committee Establishment, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 347)
  - Budgets and Proposals, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 348)
  - Conferences, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 349)
  - Institute on International Education (IIE), 1983-1984 (Box 32, Folder 350)
  - Personnel, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 351)
  - Foundation Correspondence, 1984 (Box 32, Folder 352)
  - Committee Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 353)
  - Press Clippings, 1984-1986 (Box 33, Folder 354)
  - Unsolicited Candidates, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 355)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication, People's Republic of China/Distinguished Scholar Exchange Program, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 356)
  - National Endowment of the Humanities, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 357)
  - Council on Religion and International Affairs (CRIA), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 358)
  - The Heritage Foundation, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 359)
  - The Brookings Institute, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 360)
  - Columbia University, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 361)
  - Harvard University, 1983 (Box 33, Folder 362)
  - Michigan State University, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 363)
  - School of Advanced International Studies (SAIS), Johns Hopkins University, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 364)
  - Stanford University, 1984-1986 (Box 33, Folder 365)
  - University of California, Berkeley, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 366)
  - University of Texas, Gordon Bennett, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 367)
  - The Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 368)
  - Beijing Institute for International Studies (BIISS), 1984, 1986 (Box 33, Folder 369)
  - Beijing University (BEIDA), 1982, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 370)
  - Beijing University (BEIDA), 1982, 1984 (Box 33, Folder 370A)
  - Center for International Studies, 1985 (Box 33, Folder 371)
  - Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS), 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 372)
  - Shanghai Academy of Social Sciences (SASS), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 373)
  - Institute of International Studies (IIS), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 374)
  - Institute of Contemporary International Relations (ICIR), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 375)
  - Nanjing University, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 376)
  - Nankai University, Chinese Enterprise Management Association (CEMA), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 377)
  - Shanghai Institute for International Studies (SIIS), 1984 (Box 33, Folder 378)
  - Sino-American Educational and Exchange Conferences, 1984-1985 (Box 33, Folder 379)
  - Notes on Conference Sessions (Box 33, Folder 380)
  - Sino-American Educational and Cultural Exchange: Comparative Experience, 1985 February, 1983-1985 (Box 34, Folder 381-382)
  - Conference, 1984-1985 (Box 34, Folder 383)
  - Papers, 1985 (Box 34, Folder 384-385)
  - Conference at the East-West Center, 1984-1985 (Box 34, Folder 386)
  - General Correspondence and Related Materials, 1976, 1978, 1982-1986 (Box 35, Folder 387-388)